Register of the Dimitriĭ Petrovich Pershin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Dimitriĭ Petrovich Pershin papers
1914-1950
XX535
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, diaries, writings, notes, and clippings relating to White Russian and Soviet activities in Mongolia during the Russian Revolution, and the Russian émigré population during the Russian Civil War and subsequent years. Includes a memoir entitled Baron Ungern, Urga i Altan-Bulak: Zapiski Ochevidtsa Smutnom Vremeni vo Vneshneĭ (Khakhaskoĭ) Mongoliĭ v Pervoĭ Treti II-go Veka relating to counter-revolutionary events in Mongolia during the Russian Revolution, and a translation by Elena Varneck of the memoir. Microfilm copies of memoir and translation available (2 reels).
Pershin, Dimitriĭ Petrovich.
Varneck, Elena, 1891-1976.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Microfilm copies of memoir Baron Ungern, Urga i Altan-Bulak: Zapiski Ochevidtsa Smutnom Vremeni vo Vneshneĭ (Khakhaskoĭ) Mongoliĭ v Pervoĭ Treti II-go Veka and translation by Elena Varneck available (2 reels).
Related Materials
Baron Roman Fedorovich Ungern-Shternberg miscellaneous writings, Hoover Institution Archives
N. M. Riabukhin typescript: The story of Baron Ungern-Shternberg, Hoover Institution Archives
Sergei Lavrov holograph: Sobytiia v Mongolii-Khalkhie, 1920-1921 godakh: voenno-istoricheskii ocherk-vospominaniia, Hoover Institution Archives
N. N. Kniazev typescript: The legendary baron: from reminiscences about Lieutenant-General Baron Ungern, Hoover Institution Archives
Boris N. Volkov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Elena Varneck papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Dimitriĭ Petrovich Pershin was a White Russian diplomat in Mongolia from 1918 to 1921, a Russian historian and novelist, and subsequently a Russian émigré in China.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of the writings of Pershin, as well as some correspondence and a small amount of biographical material. Among his writings is the memoir Baron Ungern, Urga i Altan-Bulak: Zapiski Ochevidtsa Smutnom Vremeni vo Vneshneĭ (Khakhaskoĭ) Mongoliĭ v Pervoĭ Treti II-go Veka, based on his experiences in Siberia, the Transbaikal region of the Far East, and Mongolia between 1918 and 1921. The memoirs include notes, research materials, holographs, typescripts, and a final draft. The papers also include an English translation of the memoir by Russian-American historian Elena Varneck.
Ungern-Sternberg, Roman, 1885-1921.; Russians--East Asia.; Mongolia--History.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
- Biographical File, 1914-1930 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes certificates of Mongolian government awards, a travel document, and son Oleg Dmitrievich Pershin's residential permits.
- Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 1)
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Unidentified, 1929-1934 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Belorukova, IU., 1933-1935 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Egorov, G. S., 1935 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Grinevich, F., 1932-1935 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Iden-Zeller, A., 1932 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Kozlov, E., 1935 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Liubushkin, V. I., 1934 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Marsh, O., 1935 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Perevaloff, I. I., 1935 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Pershin, O. D. (son), 1929-1931 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Pershin, Z. (wife), 1930-1936 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Porfirii, Ieronim, 1935 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Prostoff, M., 1931-1933 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Redkin, K., 1932-1934 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Rovensky, L. P., 1935 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Smit, A., circa 1930 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Svechnikov, A., 1929 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Vasiliev-Dubrovsky, A. N., 1932 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Vylegzhanin, circa 1930 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Walkoff, B., 1927 (Box-folder 1: 20)
- Writings, 1914-1950 (Boxes 1-3)
  Consists of articles and memoirs, including notes, research papers, holographs, and typescripts. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Untitled holographs, circa 1920 (Box-folder 1: 21-25)
  - "Baron Ungern, Urga i Altan-Bulak. Zapiski ochevidtsa o smutnom vremeni vo vneshneĭ (Khalkhaskoĭ) Mongolii v pervoĭ treti XX-go veka,", circa 1930 (Box-folder 2: 1-4)
    Includes holograph, typescript, and English translation by Elena Varneck, 1950.
  - "IUzhnaia (Vnutrenniaia) Mongoliia," holograph, circa 1930 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Iz Irkutska v Tunkinskii krai (iz dorozhnykh ocherkov), clippings, circa 1930 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Iz istorii buddizma," holograph, circa 1920 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Koe-chto o chae, clippings, 1931 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Komintern i Mongoliia, clipping, circa 1930 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "Kulinarnyi etud," holograph, circa 1920 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "Nabroski i zametki o Severnom Kitae i oboikh Mongoliiakh," holograph, circa 1920 (Box-folder 3: 6-7)
  - "Po Mongolii," holograph, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Po Zabaikal'iu, clippings, circa 1930 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Tibetskie Dalai-lamy, clippings, 1931 (Box-folder 3: 10)